Sam Houston Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Sam Houston Collection
1810-1871
Sam Houston, 1793-1863
These 43 documents are all linked to Sam Houston or his family. The bulk of them bear his signature.
1 box, .5 linear feet
1964-002
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Samuel Houston, known as the Father of Texas, was born on March 2, 1793, in Virginia. His father, Samuel Houston, was a veteran of the Revolutionary War. Following his father's death in 1807, his mother, Elizabeth (Paxton) Houston moved the family to Tennessee. Sam Houston did not have a formal education, instead attending school when possible.
Sam Houston had an active political life. Trained in law, he was elected as district attorney for Nashville at the age of 25. Soon after, he was appointed adjutant general of Tennessee. He was elected to Congress from Tennessee in 1823 and again in 1825. In 1827 he was elected governor of Tennessee. He resigned from this position in 1829 and began working in Indian territory for the Cherokees. He was made a member of the Cherokee Nation.
Houston first traveled in Texas in 1832. He attended the Convention of 1833 as a delegate from Nacogdoches, although he does not appear to have been a long-term resident of the area until 1835. In November 1835 he was elected major general of the Texas Army. He signed the Texas Declaration of Independence on March 2, 1836. On April 21, 1836, he led the Texas Army to victory over the forces of General Santa Anna in the Battle of San Jacinto.
On September 5, 1836, Houston was elected President of the Republic of Texas. September 6, 1841, he was elected again to that position, having served as a representative to the Texas Congress during Mirabeau Lamar's presidency. On February 21, 1846, Houston was elected to the U. S. Senate where he served almost 14 years. In 1859 he was elected as governor of Texas. Because he did not support the dissolution of the Union, he was removed from office in 1861.
Sam Houston died on July 26, 1863, on his farm near Huntsville, Texas.
Additional Sources:
Sue Flanagan. Sam Houston's Texas. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1964.
Sam Houston. Life of General Sam Houston: A Short Biography. Austin: Pemberton Press, 1964.
John Hoyt Williams. Sam Houston: A Biography of the Father of Texas. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1993.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes letters and documents signed by Sam Houston between 1813 and 1861. There are also several undated items as well as two letters written by Sam Houston's son, Sam Houston, in 1868 and 1871 following his father's death. There are a total of 43 items in the collection with the bulk of the items dating between 1836 and 1861.
Materials generally relate to Houston's political activities at the time. Items written or signed during 1836 relate to the Texas Revolution or Houston's role as president of the Republic of Texas. Materials from the 1840s were signed during his tenure as President of the Republic of Texas or Senator from Texas. During the 1860s materials relate to his activities as governor of Texas. Most items are financial or business papers from the government for which Houston worked.
Subjects (Persons)
Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.
Subjects
Governors -- Texas.; Legislators -- United States.; United States. Congress. Senate.; Texas -- History -- To 1846.
Formats
Correspondence
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition:
Twenty-six pieces of this collection were presented to the University of Houston in 1981 by Mary Grace and Frank P. Horlock. In 1988 these were combined with Sam Houston materials variously donated by Frell Albright, William B. Bates, Tom Elrod, and George M. Britton.
Detailed Description
- Houston, Sam. ALS. Fort St. Charles. Nov. 29, 1813. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Bond (State of Tennessee) executed and signed. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Land grant (State of Tennessee), No. 7360. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Houston, Sam. Petition for Divorce. Nov. 30, 1833. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Endorsement signature. April 4, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Discharge paper for 1st Lieutenant William H. Steele, San Jacinto Camp. April 26, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Autograph endorsement. May 25, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Promissory note, New Orleans. June 7, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Discharge paper for N. W. Burditt, San Augustine. June 15, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Discharge paper for Edward S. Jones, Nacogdoches. Sept. 13, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Resolution for the sale of bonds. Dec. 24, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Houston, Sam, to Henry Smith. LS. Dec. 26, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Houston, Sam. Endorsement. Dec. 2, 1837. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Houston, Sam. First Texian Loan Scrip. June 20, 1838. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Bond and contract for printing. Dec. 29, 1841. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Washington on Brazos. May 23, 1841. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Voucher, Washington on Brazos. Dec. 14, 1843. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Receipt, Washington on Brazos. Feb. 16, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Order for payment, Washington on Brazos. Jan. 2, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Invoice and receipt for transporting Indian prisoners. April 1, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Treasury warrant. April 1, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Washington on Brazos. Nov. 27, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Washington on Brazos. Dec. 4, 1844. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Houston, Sam. ALS. Houston. Dec. 20, 1845. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Houston, Sam. ALS. Washington on Brazos. April 24, 1846. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Houston, Sam. ALS. Senate Chamber. April 17, 1848. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Houston, Sam. LS to President James K. Polk, [1846-1848]. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Endorsement signature. 1854. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Hunt, Z. ALS to Sam Houston. Bellville. Jan. 24, 1855. (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Houston, Sam. ALS. Washington on Brazos. Feb. 10, 1855. (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Deed, Huntsville. Oct. 11, 1858. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Treasury warrant, Austin. July 10, 1860. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Treasury warrant, Austin. Nov. 17, 1860. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Houston, Sam. Broadside, signed in type. 2 copies. 1860. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Houston, Sam. DS. Treasury warrant, Austin. Feb. 8, 1861. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Houston, Sam. Broadside. Feb. 9, 1861. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Houston, Sam. Free franked envelope, Washington, D.C. Feb. 11. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Houston, Sam. DS. n. d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Photograph reproduction of portrait. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photograph reproduction of portrait. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Houston, Samuel. ALS to F. I. Govee. Nov. 13, 1868. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Houston, Samuel. ALS to Rodney A. Murcul, Georgetown, Texas. July 6, 1871. (Box 1, Folder 42)